I Can't Stay Put at One Job; I Lose Interest and Keep Moving Around.
한 직장에 재미를 못 느끼고 계속 옮겨 다녀요
Nice to meet you. Sunim
반갑습니다, 스님
I have worked in a variety of areas
저는 지금까지 직장을 한 가지 방향으로 연결해서 나가지 않고,
not being able to choose one particular field to focus on
성격이 다른 여러 가지 분야를 선택해 왔습니다.
because I have diverse interests but I tend to feel that
여러 가지에 관심이 많은 탓도 있지만
when I settle in one job I find the work to be without much merit.
전체적으로 비효율적이고 소모적이고,
I tend to conclude that the work is not necessarily helpful for the world.
또 결론적으로 세상에 별로 도움이 안 되는 일이라는 그런 생각이 듭니다.
So, I lose interest after a short time.
그래서 얼마 가지 않아서 재미를 느끼지 못하게 됩니다.
Even now I feel somewhat doubtful about the work I recently started.
지금도 현재 새롭게 시작한 일에 회의를 조금 느끼고 있는 중인데요.
What I would like to ask you is: should one accept
제가 드리고 싶은 질문은 사람이 하는 모든 일이 다 그냥 그런 거라고 생각하고
When you go to a mountain, you see some squirrels, right?
그러니까 산에 가면 다람쥐 있죠?
You see that the squirrels climb up trees
다람쥐가 나무에 올라가고 바위도 타고 넘고 이렇게 다니지 않습니까?
(Questioner) No, they do not.
(질문자) 안 그렇죠.
You need to live the way the squirrels live.
자기가 좀 다람쥐처럼 살아.
You are not even comparable to the squirrels.
지금 자기는 다람쥐보다 못한 거야.
Things never turn out the way we wish because of so many differences in people.
이 세상 사람이 다 서로 다르기 때문에 내 생각대로 되는 사람은 아무도 없어요.
Over here people are like this, over there they are like that.
여기 가면 이런 사람 있고 저기 가면 저런 사람 있고 그런 거요.
The problem is not in the jobs but within yourself.
그거는 내가 가서 직장이 문제가 아니라 자기가 문제다 이런 얘기에요.
It doesn't mean that all jobs are fine. This is how the world is.
직장이 그러면 다 잘했다는게 아니라 원래 세상살이가 그렇다는 거요.
This is how things work.
원래 세상살이가.
America looks great from here. But, being in America, you see many problems.
미국 가서 들여다 보면 여기서 보면 다 좋아보이지만 가서 보면 문제가 있고,
We seem to have many problems in Korea but if they look at us from abroad,
한국에 살면서 여러분 한국에 문제가 많다 그러지만은 외국에서 저 베트남이나 캄보디아나
say from Vietnam or Cambodia,
이런데서 보면 한국이 문제 있는게 보일까? 좋은 것만 보일까?
they will only see good things about us.
좋은 것만 보여.
If you were a teacher, you would see many corruptions
선생님 해보면 교육계 안에 비리가 많아요? 안 많아요?
If you were a Buddhist monk, you'd see many corruptions in the world of monks.
스님이 서 불교 안에 들어와 보면 스님들 세상에 비리가 많을까? 안 많을까?
A lot.
많아요. 아시겠어요?
If in the politics, you'd find many corruptions there, too.
정치권에 들어가서 그 안에 들여다 보면 비리가 많을까? 안 많을까?
A lot.
많아요.
So, wherever you look, you would find a lot of such contradictions.
그니까 어디든 들어가서 보면 다 이런저런 모순이 있습니다.
Got it?
아시겠어요?
By acknowledging the problems
그러나 우리가 그런 속에서 현실을 인정하고
But this doesn't mean that we do nothing about the troubles.
두 번째, 내버려 두자는 게 아니라
We must do whatever we can to improve the situations.
조금씩 자기 감당할 범위 안에서 개선해 나가면 되는데,
But you just notice the problems
자기는 여기 가 보니 이게 문제니까 그만두고
here, there and everywhere.
저기 가보면 저게 문제니까 그만두고
Because this world is so awful,
자기가 뭐 세상이 더럽다고 그만두고 머리 깎고 비구니 되겠다고
if you were to become a Buddhist monk,
어디 한 번 들어가 봐라.
you will not last 3 days at best.
자기 사흘도 못 견디고 또 나온다.
You will see that things are wrong there, too.
카~ 여기도 썩었구나. 저기 가면 저것도 썩었구나. 이렇게 돼.
How many years at your current job?
지금 들어간 직장에 몇 년 됐어, 들어간지?
(Questioner) Only a few months.
(질문자) 몇 달밖에 안 됐어요.
Only a few months?
몇 달밖에 안 됐어?
Then stay at this job for 3 years regardless whether you like or not.
그러면 이 직장이 좋고 나쁘고 관계 없이 삼 년을 근무하고 나와.
(Questioner) I don't change jobs in a matter of months. I do stay a while..
(질문자) 그런데 제가 몇 달씩 다니고 옮겨다니는 건 아니고. 오랫동안 다니고…
So, stay at the current job for 3 years.
아니 아니 그러니까 이 직장에 삼 년은 다녀라.
Not just stay put. For 3 years, you turn your judgmental thoughts back to yourself
그냥 직장을 다니라는 게 아니라 삼 년을 일어나는 분별심을
and you do this in a prayerful manner.
내 쪽으로 돌이키면서 기도하면서 다녀라. 이말이야.
You can quit after 3 years of noticing
그러면 이 직장이.. 일어나는 분별심, 이거 저거 문제가 되는 걸
that it is you who raise the judgmental thoughts
아, 내 분별심이구나. 이렇게 돌이켜서 삼 년을 이 고비를 넘기면
when a variety of things occur.
자기가 이 직장을 그만둬도 괜찮다 이거야
It is your judgmental thoughts that are the problems everywhere.
어디를 가도 자기가 이미 자기 분별심인줄 알기 때문에..
Are you married? (Questioner) No.
결혼했어요? (질문자) 아니요.
You must not get married in this state.
자기 결혼하면 안 돼 지금.
No matter how great a man seems before marriage,
결혼해 보면 아무리 바깥에서 좋던 남자도 살아보면 문제가 많아.
you would see flaws after a while. Got it?
아시겠어요?
A guy may spit when he talks, another one may stink,
어떤 인간은 말할 때 침 튀기고, 어떤 인간은 몸에서 냄새 나고 ,
another guy may not wash his feet, another one may not change clothes,
어떤 인간은 발 안 씻고 들어오고, 어떤 인간은 옷 안 갈아입고…
There will be numerous problems.
살아보면 다 문제 투성이에요. 알았어요?
Don't think of this only as your problem. Take this on as subject of your practice.
그러니까 이것을 직장 다니는게 핵심이 아니고 이것을 수행의 과제로 삼아라.
No matter what sort of problem arises, do not blame others.
여기서 일어나는 어떤 문제도 상대를 탓하지 말고 내 분별심이구나.
Realize your judgmental thoughts. Become aware of your own thoughts.
내가 이렇게 분별하구나. 이렇게 돌이키면서 수행으로 삼아서
Stick to your job for 3 years.
한 삼 년 한 번 다녀보세요.
(Questioner) May I ask you one question? (Sunim) Yes.
(질문자) 하나만 여쭤봐도 될까요? (스님) 네
(Questioner) You said that we live simply like a squirrel or other animals.
(질문자) 다람쥐나 동물처럼 단순하게 살라고 말씀하셨는데
(Questioner) I understood your point, but since humans can feel and think,
(질문자) 말씀하신 요지는 알겠지만 인간이 느끼고 생각하고 이런 능력이 있는 이상
(Questioner) how can we live so simply and enjoy our lives
(질문자) 그렇게 단순하게 살 수도 없고, 이런 인생의 재미를
(Questioner) like a squirrel?
(질문자) 다람쥐와 같이 똑같이 느끼면서 살 수는 없다고 생각하거든요.
You are right.
네, 맞는 얘기야.
(Questioner) And in order to improve, we ought to
(질문자) 그리고 더 발전하려면 어떤 식으로든… 그게 무슨...
But right now, you are not even at the level of the squirrels.
그러니까 자기는 지금 다람쥐보다 못 하기 때문에
You need to get on the same level as them at least.
다람쥐만큼이라도 되라. 이 얘기고.
If you become at the level of the squirrels,
다람쥐만큼 되면,
Or as for getting to a higher level than they.
이제 사람이 더 다람쥐보다 높이 갈려면,
Do squirrels help their neighbors in trouble or not?
다람쥐는 이웃 다람쥐 힘든다고 도와주나? 안 도와주나?
They do not.
안 도와주지?
If you want to be a higher level than the squirrels,
그러니까 자기가 다람쥐보다 높이 갈려면
the squirrels are also not very unhappy.
다람쥐는 괴롭진 않잖아, 그지?
But you are not very happy.
자기는 괴롭게 살잖아.
(Questioner) I am not unhappy.
(질문자) 괴롭지는 않습니다
But you make conflicts with others, don't you?
그럼 자기는 시비하잖아.
To be in conflicts with others causes pain.
시비 해요? 안 해요?
Doesn't that make you unhappy? Aren't you troubled by the thoughts
시비하는게 괴롭지. 그럼 시비하는게 안 괴로워?
such as," why is that person doing that?"
아이고 저기 뭐 저런게 다 있노? 저기 뭐 저런게 다 있노? 왜 저럴게 하나?
"how can he be like that, etc?"
이게 괴로운거 아니야?
That is being lower than the squirrels.
그러니까 다람쥐보다 못하다 이 말이여.
Some people live worse than the squirrels, some live at the level of the squirrels,
인생이 다람쥐보다 못한 인생이 있고, 다람쥐만한 인생이 있고
and some live at the higher level.
다람쥐보다 나은 인생이 있는데,
But you are living below the level of squirrels right now.
자기는 지금 다람쥐보다 못 하니까
So, I am using a squirrel's life as a benchmark.
스님이 뭐를 기준으로 제시한다? 다람쥐를 제시하는 거에요.
If you were living as well as a squirrel free of problems
자기가 다람쥐만큼 세상 사는데 뭐 별 문제의식 없이,
or even with problems,
문제는 있지만 거기에 별 구애 안 받고 살면,
if you were not burdened by them, and then asked me if this is all in life,
그러면서 이게 인생의 전부냐고 물으면
I'd say no.
아니다. 다람쥐보다 낫게 살아야 한다.
I am saying that even squirrels can live as well.
그 정도 살라면 다람쥐도 그 정도는 산다. 이렇게 말하지.
Then if you ask how do I live better?
그러면 다람쥐보다 낫게 살려면 어떻게 해야 돼요?
You ought to be able to help others in distress.
다른 사람을 도와주고, 어려운 사람 도와주고,
Even when you're hungry if you see another hungry, you share your food.
내가 배고픈데도 배고픈 사람 보면 내 배고픈 밥을 떠 주기도 하고
You ought to live a life that can be helpful to others.
그 다음에 남을 위해서 돕는 인생을 살아야 되겠지.
Living engrossed in your own discomfort is living a life below the squirrel.
내 괴로움에 빠져 있는 거는 다람쥐보다 못한 인생이고,
Sharing your happiness with others is living a life better than a squirrel.
내 기쁨을 이웃에 나눠주는 삶을 사는 거는 다람쥐보다 나은 삶이다. 이거에요.
I am telling you to live like a squirrel since you lives lower than squirrel does.
근데 자기는 지금 다람쥐보다 못하니까 스님이 다람쥐라도 되라 이런 얘기 하는 거에요.
Ask me again when you live like a squirrel Tell you how to live better.
다람쥐 되고 나서 또 물으세요. 내 다람쥐보다 나은 거 가르쳐 드릴테니까.
The animals have feelings
그러니까 여러 가지 느끼고 감정하는게
but they have no feelings of jealousy or envy.
짐승은 시기 질투 안 한다 이 말이에요.
Got it?
아시겠어요?
But they also do not have compassion to help others, either.
그렇다고 짐승은 불쌍하게 여겨서 도와주지도 않잖아? 그지?
But humans get jealous and competitive. In jealousy and competitions we fall
근데 인간은 시기 질투하잖아. 그지?
Having compassion for others is being better than animals.
남을 불쌍히 여기는 건 짐승보다 나은 거라는 거에요.
You ought to improve the aspects of yourself
그니까 자기가 지금 짐승보다 못한 부분을 우선 극복을 해서
that fall below the level of a squirrel.
그냥 한 마리 다람쥐 정도는 되라.
First, you ought to live as well as a squirrel at the very least.
그 다음에 어때요? 짐승보다 나은 길을 가야된다.
And then you can move onto a path that is better than that of the animals.
이 얘기 제가 하려는 거에요.
(Questioner) Thank you.
(질문자) 감사합니다
Stick to your job for 3 years.
한 삼 년 다니세요.
(Questioner) I will think about it. (Audience Laughter)
(질문자)생각해 보겠습니다. (청중 웃음/박수)